Niranjan Kumar

niranjankumar@gatech.edu | linkedin.com/in/kniranjankumar | kniranjankumar.com

RESEARCH STATEMENT

The goal of my research is to build embodied agents that interactively explore and improve their understanding of objects around them. My current research focus is on teaching quadruped robots explore cluttered indoor scenes. More broadly, I am interested in applying machine learning techniques to tackle problems in computer vision, robotic manipulation and quadruped locomotion.

EDUCATION

Georgia Institute of Technology

Atlanta, GA

PhD in Electrical and Computer Engineering, GPA 4.0/4.0

Jan. 2017 - Present

Georgia Institute of Technology

Atlanta, GA

Master of Science in Electrical and Computer Engineering, GPA 4.0/4.0

Aug. 2015 - Aug.2017

National Institute of Technology

Trichy, India

Bachelor of Technology in Electrical and Electronics Engineering, GPA 8.3/10

July. 2011 - May 2015

Publications

- 1. K. N. Kumar, I. Essa, and S. Ha. Graph-based Cluttered Scene Generation and Interactive Exploration using Reinforcement Learning. *ICRA 2022*, May 2022
- 2. K. N. Kumar, I. Essa, S. Ha, and C. K. Liu. Estimating Mass Distribution of Articulated Objects using Non-prehensile Manipulation. *NeurIPS Workshop on Object Representations for Learning and Reasoning (Oral)*, Dec 2020

EXPERIENCE

Graduate Teaching/Research Assistant

Jan 2017 – Present

Georgia Institute of Technology

Atlanta, GA

- GTA for 6475 Graduate Computational Photography course
- Responsibilities: Designing assignments, grading, discussions on Piazza

Research Intern

May 2019 – July 2019

Samsung Research America

Mountain View, CA

- ullet Interned at the AI center and worked on long-range video understanding using neural networks
- Investigated the applicability of graphical representations of video to tackle few shot video classification

Research Intern

June 2018 – August 2018

 $Nokia\ Bell\ Labs$

New Providence, NJ

- Interned with the Mathematics and Algorithms group at Bell labs and worked on training procedures that make neural networks robust to adversarial attacks
- Studied the effect of weight normalization techniques on the loss landscape of neural networks

Research Intern

Aug 2016 – Dec 2016

Emory University School of Medicine

Atlanta, GA

- Designed and developed a smart head-mounted eye dropper device that automatically administers eye drops into the user's eyes.
- The device has a built-in camera that tracks the drop as it falls into the user's eye with an ML model, and re-administers it in-case of failure.

Searching for objects in Indoor Environments

Aug 2021 – present

 Learning control policies for a quadruped robot to interactively search for objects in an indoor cluttered environment.

Object search in clutter

Aug 2020 – Aug 2021

- Built a scene grammar to represent structured clutter and used it as a unifying representation to generate and rearrange structured clutter.
- Developed a framework to train RL agents that generate complex cluttered scenes and then rearrange them to discover hidden objects.
- Tested the policies trained in simulation by deploying them on a real cluttered scene with a UR10 robot (sim2real).

Mass estimation of articulated objects

Aug 2018 – May 2019

- Designed RL policies to efficiently interact with articulated objects and estimate their mass distribution.
- Developed a two-network approach to interactive perception, where a Predictor network minimizes estimation error, and a Policy network selects optimal actions that reveal the most information.
- Tested the approach with a real UR10 robot (sim2real) and 3D printed articulated toys that can have an arbitrary mass distribution.

Realistic object manipulation video generation

Aug 2018 – May 2019

• Trained an Image2Image Generative Adversarial Network (GAN) that generates realistic videos of hands manipulating objects from motion capture data.

Eye-dropper device

Jan 2016 – Dec 2016

- Designed and built an intelligent eye-dropper that automatically administers eye drops to a patient's eye.
- Developed and implemented a machine learning based approach to classify an image of the eye as open or closed. The algorithm is light-weight and can run on a Raspberry Pi mounted within the device.
- Designed and fabricated an electro-mechanical system that administers medication when the eye is open and tracks the drop to ensure that it enters the eye.

Selecting real world objects with eye gaze

Jan 2016 - May 2016

• Built a system that helps paralyzed patients select objects of interest from a scene with an eye-gaze tracker. The objects of interest are detected and tracked by using SURF features.

Graduate Coursework

Interactive Robot Learning
Statistical Techniques for Robotics
Mathematical Foundations for ML
Statistical Machine Learning
Control of Robotic Systems
Intro to Graduate Algorithms

Computer Vision
Advanced Computer Vision
Computational Photography
PDEs for Image Processing and CV
Digital Image Processing
Linear Systems and Control

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Languages: Python

Developer Tools: Git, Docker, VS Code, Visual Studio, PyCharm

Libraries/Packages: NumPy, Scipy, Matplotlib, Pandas, Jupyter, OpenCV, ROS, MATLAB

Neural Network Libraries: Tensorflow, Pytorch Physics Libraries: Pybullet, Pydart, Issac Gym

Robots: UR10, TurtleBot, Unitree A1